Mss.Ms.Coll.104
American Philosophical Society
Hare-Willing Family Papers
1724-1965
Mss.Ms.Coll.104
American Philosophical Society
52.0 Linear feet 105 boxes; 151 volumes
This is a collection of letters, letterbooks, account books, scrapbooks, etc., concerning the families of Robert Hare and Thomas Willing. The letters and other documents include early family material, as well as documents written by numerous family relations, and some obviously only collected by them. The Willing family letters (1744-1901) are diverse, concerning family matters, business, society, comments on the Civil War, etc. There are numerous letters from Thomas Willing, many concerning his banking career, as President of the Bank of North America and later at the first Bank of the U.S. The Hare family letters (1724-1965) are more extensive and diverse, including much on travel in the U.S. and elsewhere. There is a letter from Robert Hare Jr. concerning steam engines, and letters from Horace Binney Hare concerning his education at Harvard, 1860, his trip to San Francisco and the west, 1862, and numerous letters written while a soldier in the Civil War. There are many letters from Horace Binney (1780-1875, DAB) to his daughter Esther, who was married to John Innes Clark Hare (1816-1905, DAB), concerning family travel and court cases. There are also letters from outside the family, such as those from Dorothea L. Dix. The bound volumes include, among others: Robert Hare letterbooks (1824-1825, 1841-1857), estate records, and laboratory expense accounts (1818-1860); G. H. Hare's journal or log of cruises aboard the U.S. United States (1841) and U.S. Flint (1845); Horace Binney Hare's 1862 journal of his trip to San Francisco. There are account books and accounts (1754-1795) kept by Thomas Willing; accounts of the controversy over the estate of John Innes Clark; and records of the First Colored Wesley Methodist Church of Philadelphia (receipt book, 1820-1848; minute book, 1827-1844). There are also Philadelphia court records, and minutes of the Common Council of the city, 1832.
Hare-Willing family.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Mrs. Henry Meigs and Truxtun Hare, Jr., and accessioned, 04/28/1981 (1981 1624ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Robert Hare, an English immigrant in 1773, was a prominent businessman and served in the Pennsylvania legislature and as a trustee of the University of Pennsylvania. He married Margaret Willing, sister of Thomas Willing, who was a banker and official and legislator in Pennsylvania. Their son, Robert, was a chemist and inventor and taught at the University of Pennsylvania. In the third generation, John Innes Clark Hare was a distinguished Philadelphia judge. His son, Dr. Horace Binney Hare was an instructor of Chemistry and professor of Hygiene. Married to Emily Power Beale in 1868, they had five children, Robert Hare, Charles Willing Hare, Esther Binney Hare, Horace Binney Hare, married to Ellen Mary Cassatt, and Thomas Truxtun Hare, a track and field Olympic medal winner in 1900, 1904.
African American History Note
Of particular interest to students of African American history are records of the First Colored Wesley Methodist Church of Philadelphia (receipt book, 1820-1848; minute book, 1827-1844).
Early American History Note
This is a large and wide ranging collection on materials. The collection contains over 1300 individual items along with 53 bound volumes, which range from letter books to records of the First Colored Wesley Methodist Church. Letters to and from the various members of the extended Hare-Willing family compose the bulk of the loose correspondence.
The Willing Family papers consist of over 500 items ranging from 1744 to 1863, with the bulk from the nineteenth century. The early papers relate primarily to the business career of Thomas Willing, former partner of Robert Morris and President of the First Bank of the United States. The family was later involved in establishing the Baring Company. The letters from the 1820s onward are an assortment of personal and professional correspondence of Thomas Willing’s son, Thomas Mayne, and grandchildren, mostly between Charles Willing and his sister Elizabeth Sterling, that touch on matters political, social, cultural, and economic. Topics of discussion include poetry, literature, medical treatments, and social customs and mores, including things such as dueling and courtship. Because of their financial situation, the letters discuss important economic events, such as the Panic of 1825, which resulted in the Stirling family’s business closing. Politics is occasionally but not often discussed. Some of the records relate to the estate they received from their parents.
Numerous letters detail the family’s history, including discussions of education, travel, finance, and relationships within the family. Some of the family news is deeply personal, including discussions of medical and financial problems, miscarriage, and unhappiness with others in the family. Notably, there is a series of letters written by Charles Willing in the 1820s and 1830s from European cities, such as Milan, Rome, and Paris.
The Hare Family correspondence is equally focused on the nineteenth century. The Hare family correspondence includes letters from Robert Hare Jr., the leading chemist of his day, and Horace Binney, a leading legal thinker of his day whose daughter married into the Hare family. The nature of the Hare correspondence is very similar to the Willing correspondence, although there is more correspondence that is political in nature. Discussions include education, family matters, personal affairs, and current events. Some of the letters from the Civil War era capture the mobilization of the city.
Of particular note, the Binney correspondence discusses his involvement in the legal case regarding the Stephen Girard Estate. Girard’s heirs contested portions of his will that gave portions of his estate to charity. Binney argued successfully against the heirs’ claims, who were themselves represented by Daniel Webster, in the Supreme Court. The Court’s decision established important case law for protecting charities. The collection includes a letter Binney wrote to his wife while sitting in the Supreme Court amidst arguments. Also of some interest may be a diary kept by Charles Hare, nephew of Robert Hare, that details his escape as a British prisoner of war from the French jail at Verdun in 1809; the diary is typescript and the originals are not part of the collection.
The major difference between the Hare and the Willing portions of the collection – aside from the letter writers - is the chronological focus. The Hare collection is particularly focused in the 1840s onward. The Willing correspondence is strongest in the 1820s-1840s.
The Hare-Willing Collection also includes over 50 bound volumes that range from the colonial era to the Civil War era. The volumes are diverse and include account books, receipt books, letter books, travel journals, and minute books from Philadelphia organizations. A chronological list of the books with brief descriptions follows:
1. Accounts of Thomas Willing (1754-1760) and Estate of Capt Sam Appowen, 1767-1776 - A ledger book that records the financial transactions of Thomas Willing during his years a prominent Philadelphia merchant, including his time as partner of Robert Morris. The records of the estate of Sam Appowen are also detailed, for which Willing apparently served as executor.
2. Accounts of Thomas Willing, Thomas Willing Francis and/or the firm of Willing and Francis, 1789 – 1795 - Ledger book contains a wide array of transactions conducted, which appear to be commercial in nature and include supporting “adventures” to India, Martinique and other places abroad, which provides insight into the range of commercial activity in the early republic and the goods being brought into and sold.
3. Docket of the Court of Common Pleas of Philadelphia County – 1793-1812 -Volume lists plaintiffs and defendants with court actions
B. The Account Book of Thomas Willing, 1754-1786 - The book details Willing’s business transactions from the colonial era to the early republic, with most records coming from the post-Revolution era. Included are bank notes and other receipts, along with detailed business transactions with individuals and other firms. Records of various merchant ships are also included.
A. Estate book and Receipt book of Willing and Morris and records of the estate of Clement Plumstead, 1745-1765 - Clement Plumstead was a member of one of Philadelphia’s most prominent families. A slender volume records the management of his estate for the year 1745. A second, larger ledger book in this portion of the collection documents the receipts of Willing and Morris from 1760 to 1765.
8. Records of Wharf, 1802 - A collection of boats that came into a wharf, likely one owned by Willing, for the months of October 1802 – February 1803.
5. Accounts of Philip Wilson, 1800-1811 - Financial transcaction of Philip Wilson, captain based out of Philadelphia. Included in the front of the book are legal records from 1805 that chronicle an ill-fated voyage Wilson took from France to the U.S. aboard the Mars. He encountered a storm and brought the ship into Ireland, where he had to repair the ship and give a number of depositions for insurance reasons.
9. Thomas Willing’s Account with the Bank of the U.S., property of Charles Willing Hare, and Letters and Accounts of Thomas Mayne Willing regarding the Bingham Estate, 1810-1822 - This ledger has three types of documents. The first is a brief account of the will and estate of Charles Willing Hare. The second details Thomas Mayne Willing’s accounts and stocks held in the First Bank of the United States, an institution for which he eventually served as president. These accounts may also be related to the Hare estate. The final set are the records of the Bingham Estate, and Thomas Willing’s execution of it, which include a series of letters from the 1820s. These letters are sometimes personal and discuss a range of topics, such as attempts to have a family member receive a commission in the Navy
11. Robert Hare Accounts, 1819 and 1828 – 1846 - This large ledger books stores the daily purchases and financial transactions of Robert Hare, the noted American chemist.
13.Robet Hare – Extracts – 1823 - This appears to be a commonplace book of Robert Hare. The large folio volume contains moves through an alphabetical list of words with definitions, ideas, and other matter. It is not clear if Hare copied the content or wrote it himself, although it appears at a minimum that some of the entries are Hare’s own original thoughts.
5a – E.C. Binney’s Notebook on Orinthology - This notebook contains a list of bird species and their characteristics.
1a – Abby Willing’s Daybook – 1784-1789 This journal records the daily purchases of the Willing household, lending insight into the consumption patters and tastes of one of the more prominent Philadelphia families.
9a – Orphan’s Court Records for Bryan Wilkinson Estate, 1843 - A printed legal document relating to an audit of the Wilkinson estate.
21 – Dr. Charles Willing – Accounts, 1845-1847 - List of financial dealings of Willing that include his private accounts as well as those he managed for various estates.
19 – Clark Hare – Court cases and writings, 1842-1850 - Contains a list of court cases with defendants, plaintiffs, and the court’s action. The back contains some writings on a variety of topics, presumably by Clark Hare as well.
18 – Robert and Clark Hare Letter book, 1842-1857 - A letter book of primarily Clark Hare on a range of matters. There are some letters from Robert Hare as well.
14 – Robert Hare – Partial letter book 1824-1825 - The fragmentary letter book is a very fragile copy of Hare’s outgoing letters for primarily 1825. The letter book appears to be carbon copies, a relatively early use of this technology.
10 – Letter book regarding the Estate of John Innes Clark, 1811-1830 - The letter book contains correspondence as it relates to settling the estate of John Innes Clark, a Rhode Island based merchant. The correspondents include Robert Hare, who marries Clark’s daughter.
3a – Horace Binney Hare’s book of formula - 1861 - A collection of chemical and mathematical processes, formulas, and equations.
6 – P[hilip] Wilson Account Book - Ledger Book A of Philip Wilson for 1800-1811, recording a variety of financial transactions.
7 – Account Book, 1801-1806 - An account book from 1801-1806 of unknown ownership.
6a – Notes and Observations of England and Scotland, 1836-1837 -This is a fascinating journal, perhaps written by Robert Hare. The observations often compare society to America’s. The author, for instance, points out how political patronage in America is practiced but obscured from view, while in England it is a point of pride. Other entries involve witnessing a coal workers strike, copious notes on newspaper editorials and reports, and other cultural observations, such as the drinking culture of England.
Unnumbered – Esther Hare Account Book 1884
Unnumbered – 1830 Annals of Philadelphia by John Watson
Misc 3 – Emily Hare, Address and Account book, 1880-1882
16 – John Binney Copy book, 1859 and John I.C. Hare, 1860
17a – The Theological Commonplace book with letters to Blanche from Mary Ellen written in the blank pages, 1859-1860
70a – Legal notes on Law – mid to late 19th century
67a – Charles Willing Hare, Minutes from Blackstone’s Commentaries on Laws of England
20 – Robert Hare, Jr., Letter book, 1844-1845 - This letter book contains series of letters Hare wrote that primarily involve his business affairs.
15 – Robert Hare Jr., Letter Book, 1833-1844 - The letters in this book relate primarily to legal matters and affairs, most of which Hare is involved in one way or another.
4 – Philadelphia Court of Common Pleas and Supreme Court of Eastern Pennsylvania, 1795-1811 - This large volume contains the records of both the Philadelphia Court of Common Pleas and the Supreme Court of Eastern Pa. The records contain the names of those on trial, and occasionally details of the trial. The first half chronicles the court of Common Pleas from 1795-1811 and usually contains the docket number and names of those on trial. The records of the Supreme Court are shorter in chronology, covering the years 1803-1809.
69a – Robert Hare Chemistry Notes - Robert Hare was a leading chemist in the nineteenth century and this notebook may be of interest to historians of science. The book contains a statement written by Hare about chemistry and the job of a chemist. It is likely that this notebook served as the basis for some of Hare’s lectures.
18a – Horace Binney Hare Account book, 1860-1866 - List of purchases, marked “Private”
19a – Horace Binney Hare – Journal to San Francisco, 1862 - Sixty four page journal of Hare’s trip to San Francisco, notable for his detailed observations on San Francisco life and his “adventures” in the city.
2b – Robert Hare, Sr., Account book, 1763 - This volume is the account book of Robert Hare, Sr., Philadelphia brewer. The account book, however, is from his time in London before he traveled to Pennsylvania to establish himself. Hare appears to have been a merchant or involved in trade on some level, as many of the entries relate to ships, insurance, and exchange of consumer goods.
Unnumbered – Estate documents - A statement regarding the confusion over the estate of John Inees Clark, most likely by Robert Hare
Unnumbered – Diagrams and Plans of the Principal Battles by James Wilkinson, 1816 - This printed book contains detailed maps of various battles in American history from the Revolution to War of 1812 that Wilkinson participated in.
12 – First Colored Wesley Methodist Church, Receipt Book, 1820-1848 - Record of purchases and other financial transactions.
Misc 2 – Minute Book of First Colored Wesley Methodist Church, Minutes, 1827-1841 - The Minute Book contains a complete record of the Board of Trustee’s of the church. The actions and debates may be a rich resource for a historian of the era studying African American history.
Misc 1 – General Atlas for Carey’s Edition of Guthrie’s Geography - Rare atlas printed in Philadelphia in 1795 that includes various maps, including an atlas of lands charted by Cook and of each U.S. state.
6b – Clark Hare, Legal Notes, 1851 - Various notes, including notes of cases Hare apparently tried.
5b – Records of executor of Robert Hare’s Estate, 1846-1848 - A very brief account of the estate.
4b – Minutes of the Common Council, 1832 - Robert Hare served as clerk for the council and this volume records much of their activity.
3b – Robert Hare Account Book of Lab Expenses, 1818-1826 - This volume chronicles the purchases that Robert Hare, one of the leading chemists of his day, made for his lab and its experiments, providing insight on his equipment and the operation of his lab.
2b – Robert Hare’s Material Relating to Estate of John Innes Clark, 1813-1824 - This volume is a detailed accounting of the estates accounting, including reports on property that John Innes Clark held, including various land holdings in western territories.
15a – Diary/Commonplace, possibly of Mrs. Tillinghast, Rebecca Willing’s mother - Miscellaneous daily notes and entries
12a – The Republican Court, Rufus Griswold
11a – Robert Hare Estate, Accounts 1847-1861 - A very brief accounting of the transactions of the Robert Hare Estate
10a – Robert Hare’s Expenditures and Receipts, 1845-1858 - While this includes regular transactions of Hare, it also contains an accounting of his examination of an oyster shell and a hand drawn map.
8a – Robert Hare Letter Book 1841-1857 - A collection of letters from Robert Hare.
7a – G.H. Hare’s Journal aboard the United States (1841) and the schooner Flirt (1845) - Daily log of voyages.
Beale, Catherine C., 1857-; Beale, Charles Willing, 1845-1932; Beale, Constance R., 1849-; Beale, Edward Fitzgerald, 1853-; Binney, Horace, 1780-1875; Cassatt, Mary, 1844-1926; Clark, John Innes; Dix, Dorothea Lynde, 1802-1887; First Colored Wesley Methodist Church of Philadelphia.; Flint (Ship); Hare, Charles Willing, 1871-1942; Hare, Ellen Mary Cassatt; Hare, Emily P. Beale, 1848-1935; Hare, Esther Binney, 1873-1967; Hare, Esther Coxe Binney; Hare, George Harrison; Hare, Horace Binney, 1843-1879; Hare, Horace Binney, 1876-1956; Hare, Horace Binney; Hare, John Innes Clark, 1816-1905; Hare, Margaret Willing, 1753-1816; Hare, Robert, 1752-1811; Hare, Robert, 1781-1858; Hare, Robert, 1869-1875; Hare, Thomas Truxtun, 1878-1956; Harvard University.; Mac Veagh, Margaret; Meigs, Ellen Mary Cassatt Hare; Perry-Smith, Oliver, 1884-1969; Philadelphia (Pa.). -- Councils. -- Common Council.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Smith, Stuart Farrar, 1874-1951; United States (Ship); Willing, Thomas, 1731-1821; Account books.; African American; African American churches--United States; Americans Abroad; Banks and banking -- United States -- History -- 19th century.; Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Early National Politics; Education; Educational Material; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Institutional Records; International Travel; Journals (notebooks).; Law; Legal Records; Letterbooks.; Minutes.; Miscellaneous; Natural History; Notebooks; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs.; Philadelphia History; Receipt books.; Religion; Religion, religious organizations; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Description and travel.; Science -- United States -- 19th century.; Science and Technology; Scrapbooks.; Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform; Steam-engines.; Titantic (Steamship); Travel; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel.; Women's History; World War I; World War II
- Series I. Correspondence-Willing Family, 1744-1901
  Scope and Contents note
  Business correspondence of Thomas Willing regarding stocks, land purchases, and the Bank of North America from 1744-1822. Letters of Charles Willing to his father and from his relatives in Scotland, 1822-1883, regarding receipt of remittances and family news.
  - Thomas Willing to Richard Peters, 1744 April 28; A
    About list of books purchased and cost of same. Comments on W. McKnight and A. Palmer. Talk of peace between England and France.
  - Charles Willing's will, 1750 July 28; B
  - Thomas Lake to Willing & Lloyd, 1750 August 16; C
    Account with Thomas Lake.
  - Richard Peters to Charles Willing, 1750 December 7; D
    Refers to Indian affairs, family, opening of Academy, and 500 acres of land.
  - Bank to Mr. Willing, 1789 November 24; E
    Arrangements agreed to at bank. Security for R. Morris. Joint-bond--Morris and Willing.
  - Bank of North America, 1789 November 24; F
    Copy of minutes from Bank of North America. In reference to Mr. Morris' loan and Morris & Willing's joint bond.
  - Bank of North America, 1791 November 18; G
    Thomas Willing's proposal to resign as president of Bank of North America. (Address and minutes of Directors)
  - Directors of Bank of North America, 1791 November 18; H
    An acknowledgement to Thomas Willing on retirement as President of Bank of North America.
  - Thomas M. Willing, 1796 April 20; I
    Statement of transaction of ship Mount Vernon (Delaware) by T.M. Willing. Willing & Francis agents for Mr. Duncanson from Mr. Murgatroyd.
  - Alexander Baring to Thomas Willing, 1796 July 13; J
    Advising he's used Willing name in the purchase of land in Maine from Mr. Bingham for Henry Hope and Sir Francis Baring.
  - Bank of United States, 1796 December 30; K
    From meeting of Directors of Bank of United States, the correctness of Cashier's report.
  - Bank of United States, 1799 January 8; L
    At a meeting of the stockholders it was resolved -- President's salary -- $3,000 yr. Sum of $500 be laid out to purchase a piece of plate for President of Bank of United States as testimony for service during epidemic.
  - Robert Hare ? to Dr. Lee, 1805 November 16; M
    About Mr. Weeden's contrivance for propelling bost and improvements to be made. (steam engine power)
  - Political and Commericial Register, 1807 November 11; N
    Bank of United States reply to Thomas Willing's resignation as President of Bank of United States (signed by Samuel Breack, Chairman) and address to Directors from Thomas Willing. (Page 3, column 1)
  - Political and Commercial Register, 1807 November 14; O
    Address to Thomas Willing, retiring President of Bank of United States, from officers of Bank of United States and answer. (page 3, column 3)
  - United States Gazette, 1809 January; P
    Notice of Willing's and Francis' partnership dissolved. (page 1, column 5) Notice -- application for payment of 1/2 of bank note -- signed by T. Willing. Payment stopped. (page 1, column 2)
  - United States Gazette, 1809 May 15; Q
    "Character of Sam Breck" who died May 7, 1809.
  - Assorted letters, 1750; No. 1
    Richard Peters to Elias Bland, 1750 July 28, Indian goods order. Elias Bland, 1750 October 8, Receipt of money for goods. Charles Willing to Thomas Willing, 1750 November 17, Notice not to pay again.
  - Richard Peters to "Dear Sir", 1781 May 21; No. 2
    Dishonest attempt of Elias Bland's creditors to be paid twice. Lands in Jersey. Dr. Baird's resignation. Inquire at Mr. Penn's about papers clerk Aiskel took with him. Sermon at Academy opening and account of school.
  - Thomas Willing to Mary Willing, 1792 July 7; No. 3
    (copy of paper given by father) Estimate of property given by father at time of marriage.
  - Baring & Co. to Willing & Francis, 1797 August 14; No. 4
    Account of sales of 126 puncheons of rum. (puncheon = 84 gallons)
  - Articles of Association, 1798 June 30; No. 5
    "Macpherson's Blues".